Page 1 I will introduce the lesson
plan for the 2nd semester of 2024,
Object-Oriented Programming 2 class (CCO1102.02)
Page 2
Class hours are three hours per week
Among these, two hours from 1pm on Wednesday
will be held as offline classes,
and one hour on Friday
late evening will be replaced with a video lecture
The classroom for Wednesday
classes is D504 in the 4th Engineering Building
The lecture is taught by Professor Lee In-kwon of the Department of Computer Science,
and his email address is iklee@yonsei.ac.kr
Professor Lee In-kwon's lab
is in room D719 of the 4th Engineering Building
Interview times are basically available
one hour before or after class,
but please make reservations via email if possible
TA is made up of two people: Im Do-gyu and Baek Ha-neul
Please check TA's email address in the notes
TAs reside in the Computer Graphics Lab, Room
D712, Building 4
Page 3
This course uses the Java programming language
and provides theory
and practice of object-oriented programming
This course is intended for students
who already have programming experience,
not beginners
Object-oriented programming, or OOP for short,
is a programming language
that includes the basic
concepts of Class, Object,
Inheritance, Polymorphism,
and encapsulation
Through these concepts,
you will learn how to design
and implement efficient software systems
that are robust,
reusable, and maintainable
The overall course covers the skills
needed to solve real-world programming problems
using the Java language
Page 4
This course is intended for students
who have experience learning
at least one programming language
If you look at the basic programming courses
offered at Yonsei University,
there are a wide variety of courses
listed in this slide
Of course, in addition to this,
you can also learn basic programming courses
offered by each college
or department, or through other means
such as online lectures
even if the course is not offered in our university
That is, although this course
covers the basic programming part,
it is not suitable for people who are new to programming
because the basic part progresses very quickly
I hope these facts will help
you decide whether or not to take the course
Page 5 There is no separate textbook,
and classes are conducted solely with lecture notes
and video lectures
In fact, there are many
good textbooks that cover the Java language
and object-oriented programming,
and there are many good lectures, both paid and free, on the Internet
Among them, if we look at the references
that have recently received good reviews,
there is a Korean textbook called "This is Java" by Shin Yong-kwon and Lim
Gyeong-gyun, and among the English textbooks, there is "Java:
The Comprehensive Guide to Java
Programming for Professionals" by Christian Ullenboom
Page 6 I will introduce the class
organization
Students watch the lecture
notes and recorded video lectures
provided each week and take and submit quizzes
Additionally, students are given three or four programming assignment
problems each week
Students can discuss and solve these problems with their teammates
during the practice class
held during offline lectures on Wednesdays
Any problems that were not solved during the practice class
must be submitted by midnight the following Tuesday
Programming exercises and assignment
submissions are conducted through an auto-judge server
The auto-judge server automatically grades the programs
submitted by students
and accepts assignment submissions
if the submitted programs function properly
and satisfy all the conditions of the problem
The midterm and final exams,
which are the most important in evaluating grades, are closed-book
written exams and include various types of questions such as coding,
subjective, short answer, and multiple choice
Page 7
Let me tell you about the grading criteria
that you are most interested in
This subject is a relative evaluation subject
Therefore, the maximum ratio of A and B grades is limited
For reference, I have been giving almost the maximum ratio of A and B grades
in cases where there are no special circumstances
The detailed grading criteria are: midterm and final exams are 35% each,
Programming assignments are graded at 15%, quizzes at 10%, attendance
at 3%, and Classum participation at 2%
All questions and answers will be made through Classum
Students can anonymously share questions, answers,
useful information, etc
Participation scores are based on your engagement with answers
and helpful information
In addition to attendance, this course uses a designated seating system
From the second week onwards, three members of the same team will sit together
Therefore, attendance check will be done by TA
Also, attendance for one hour on Friday
will be automatically checked based on whether or not you watched the video lecture,
so please be sure to watch the lecture video
Page 8 Let's take a quick
look at the weekly study schedule
In the first week,
we will set up the programming environment with an introduction to
object-oriented programming and the Java language
Any lectures that were not completed during offline
class hours must be viewed as video lectures and submitted by solving the quiz
by midnight of the following Tuesday
Starting from the second week,
video lectures and quizzes will be uploaded every Wednesday
Students will watch the video lectures
and take the quizzes by midnight the following Tuesday
During offline classes on Wednesdays,
programming practice assignments will be given
based on the content learned in video lectures the previous week
Students can discuss and solve problems with their team members
during the Wednesday lab time,
and are free to ask questions to TAs and professors
Solutions to the coding assignments must be submitted to the auto-judge
server and accepted by midnight the following Tuesday
The learning content for the second week includes Java
basic programming before OOP concepts, i.e
Operator, Control Structure, Screen Input/Output, and String class
In the third week, we will learn about reference types,
arrays, and enumeration types that we need to know before learning the full-fledged OOP concepts
The class on September 18, which is the Chuseok holiday period, will be replaced with a video lecture
Over the 4th and 5th weeks, we will learn about classes,
the most basic OOP concept
Since the content is large, we split it over two weeks
In the 4th week, we will learn about
the concepts of class, object, instance,
fields such as variables and constants, and constructors
In week 5, we will learn about methods,
the difference between instances and static members, packages and access modifiers
In week 6, we will learn about inheritance,
a very important concept in OOP
We will learn about the concepts of type conversion and polymorphism,
and the meaning of abstract classes
In week 7, we learn about interfaces,
which have more freedom than classes, and about nested classes
and nested interfaces
There will be a midterm exam in the 8th week
Page 9
In week 9, we will learn about exception
handling mechanisms that can handle avoidable
software errors
In week 10, we will be introduced the Object class,
which is the ancestor of all classes,
and generics that can be used by changing types
In week 11, we will learn how to perform multiple tasks simultaneously
and control their order using the
multi-threading feature provided by Java
In week 12, we will learn about the Collection Framework,
a powerful, fundamental data structure provided by Java
In week 13, we will learn about Lambda Expressions,
which allow you to create anonymous functions and process them concisely
In week 14, we will learn about Swing as a standard for
Java Graphical User Interface
There will be a final exam in the 15th week