Page 1
In this lecture, we will learn about
the concepts of object-oriented programming
Page 2
Object-Oriented Programming,
So, what is this object-oriented programming,
abbreviated as OOP?
OOP is a programming paradigm
based on the concept of Objects
Here, an object refers to a unit that combines data
and the operation
(or method, function) that processes it
OOP was developed in the 1960s
to increase the maintainability
and reusability of code
It was first introduced through languages
such as Smalltalk,
and was later widely adopted by languages such as C++ and Java
Most programming languages today
have OOP language features
Examples include Java, C++,
Python, C#, Ruby, Swift, Kotlin, Javascript, Dart, Go, etc
Page 3 What are the advantages of
using OOP?
First, modularity
Code management becomes easier by dividing the code
into independent objects
Second, reusability
Once we create an object,
we can reuse it in multiple programs
Third, scalability
We can also systematically manage
large-scale programming projects
Fourth, it is easy to maintain
That means it's easy to debug and update
Page 4 Let's compare
Procedural Programming
and Object-Oriented Programming
Procedural programming is a style of writing
code centered around functions and procedures,
and is mainly structured in a top-down manner
OOP, on the other hand,
writes code centered around objects and their interactions
Objects allow us to model real world
objects more naturally
Page 5 Let's look at some Python code
using procedural programming
techniques
First, prepare a list
called student_grades to store the students' names
and grades
Define the function "add_student_grade",
which receives the student name and grade as parameters
and adds them to the student_grades list
The "append" function of the list is used for this
Function "get_average_grade" finds the average of all grades
in the current list
As we can see so far,
the lists and functions used in the program are all defined independently
Now, we complete the desired task
by executing procedures, or functions
First, we call add_student_grade twice
to store the grades of two students,
Alice and Bob, in the student_grades list
Then call the get_average_grade function
to calculate the average score
and print it on the screen. Page 6
This Python program
shows the characteristics of OOP well
We can see that Classes representing Objects
are defined
First, the Student class has two variables
called name and grade as data,
which represent one entry object
that stores the names and grades of students
The Classroom object has a list
of students as data
In the Constructor, the list
is initialized to an empty list
In addition to data, the Classroom class
has functions that handle data
First, the add_student function
adds one entry to the students list
with the given student name and grade parameters
The get_average_grade function calculates
the average score of all entries
in the current list
In OOP, data and functions (or methods) come together to form a single object
Program execution consists of creating objects with appropriate data
and calling methods of the objects
Here, after creating an object of the Classroom class,
the add_student function of that object is called twice
to add two data entries to the list
We can see that the data entry parameter being added
is an object of the Student class
After the data is added,
the get_average_grade function of the classroom object
is called to calculate the average
and then display it on the screen
In this example, it may seem that
there is no difference between procedural
programming and object-oriented programming
However, I would like to emphasize that in OOP, Student and Classroom
are classes that consist of a combination of data and functions,
and that these classes are easy to use and manage by transplanting
their codes to other programs as they are