Page 1
In this lecture, I will briefly introduce the Java language that will
be used in this course
Page 2
First, I think it would be necessary to explain why
we chose Java for our OOP course
Java can be seen as a pure
OO language itself
Therefore, it is an ideal language for studying
the main concepts of OOP
For example, in a Java program,
all variables and methods must belong to some class
Code without a class cannot exist in Java
If we look at this Java program,
all the code is implemented within the class IdealOOP
Therefore, Java programming can be said
to be a continuous process of implementing classes
Page 3
Another reason we use Java in our course is that
although it is an older language,
it is still used in many places
For example, it is widely used in large-scale enterprise system implementation,
server implementations, the Android operating system is implemented in Java,
and it is also widely used in implementing cloud systems
Page 4
This is the TIOBE index,
which ranks programming languages
based on how frequently they are used
Here, Java, shown in orange,
has been hovering between the 1st and 2nd
place rankings since 2002 to the mid-2010s
Python, shown in blue,
began to make strides in the mid-2010s when Deep Learning emerged, and as of 2024,
it is by far the top ranking
Below that, we can see the traditionally used languages
C, C++, and Java
Page 5 Let's briefly introduce
the history of the Java language,
focusing on its application areas
In the early 1990s, Java was developed by Sun Microsystems
as a programming language for consumer electronics
Java was officially released in 1995,
and with the philosophy of "Write Once, Run Anywhere,"
it was initially used primarily for developing applications
that ran on the web, namely applets
It began to be used gradually
for corporate application development in the late 1990s
and into the 2000s, and from the mid-2000s,
it emerged as the main language for large-scale corporate system development
Page 6 In the mid-2000s,
it also began to be used in the field
of mobile application development,
and was widely used in the development of feature
phone applications in the pre-smartphone era
In the 2010s, the Android system was implemented in Java,
establishing it as the main language
for Android app development
Java is still being used in various fields today,
including web servers, enterprise systems,
Android apps, Hadoop,
a technology that processes large amounts of data
by connecting multiple computers to process
big data, and device control
for the Internet of Things (IoT)
Page 7 Java is expected to continue to be widely
used in the future
The Java language is expected to play a continued role in the development of various applications
that run on the cloud,
and its utilization in the fields of artificial intelligence and machine
learning is gradually expanding
Its importance in microservice architecture is expected to continue,
so reusable classes that are in charge of detailed functions are gradually increasing,
and its competitiveness is expected to continue through performance
improvements and support for new hardware architectures
along with the expansion of the Java ecosystem itself
through interoperability with other JVM languages that compile to byte code (Kotlin, Scala, etc.)
Page 8 Java is a cross-platform
programming language
“WORA”, or “Write Once Run
Anyware”, is the acronym for this feature of Java
To run a program written in the Java language,
we compile it with the javac compiler,
which produces a ".class" file that is expressed in "Byte Code",
an intermediate language that is the same for all types
of processors or operating systems
These .class files run in a software virtual machine
called the Java Virtual Machine (JVM)
That is, byte code can be viewed as the machine
language of the JVM
Of course, JVM is a
platform-dependent software that is implemented differently on each platform,
but since byte code has a very simple format,
the difficulty of implementing JVM is not that high
Page 9
This program is a simple program that adds the values of two integers
a and b and prints them using a class called Add
I will explain in more
detail later, but in order for a class to run as a program,
it must have a ‘main’ method,
and the program will run from the main method
First, assign the values 5 and 3 to two variables
a and b of Integer type respectively
Another integer type variable, result,
will have the value of adding a and b,
and the resulting value, result, will be printed on the screen
Page 10
The JVM has a simple stack machine architecture
As we can see in the picture, input and
output in Stack only occur in one direction
When the stack is empty, the TOP index, which teaches the Stack Top, is -1, and when one data is pushed,
it is stored in stack[TOP] and the
TOP index is increased
In this way, the push
operation stacks new data one by one on
top of the existing top element
The pop operation removes the current top element
and decreases the TOP index by one
Page 11
This program is an example of a Byte Code program
obtained as output by compiling Java source code using javac
Each line of Byte Code has a line number,
and each line can be represented by only
one byte (i.e. 8 bits or two hexadecimal digits)
Before the Byte Code Program starts, the JVM's Variable array and Stack are initialized
At Line 0, we encounter the bypush instruction (operation),
which is an instruction to push the number of bytes
(operand) immediately following it
onto the stack
The state of Variable memory and Stack after execution up to Line 1 is
shown in the figure on the right
As we can see in the picture, 5 is pushed onto
the Stack, and the top index = 0
In Line 2, the top element of the Stack is popped
and stored in V{0]
In Line 3, constant 3 is pushed onto the Stack
In Line 4, the top element of the Stack is popped
and stored in V[1]
In Lines 5 and 6, V[0] and V[1] are pushed onto the Stack
Line 7 pops two elements from the Stack, adds them, and
then pushes the result back
That is, here, 3 and 5 are popped,
added, and the result, 8, is pushed
In line 8, the top element of the Stack is popped
and saved in V[2]
Lines 9 to 12 display the result, V[2] = 8
Page 12
The byte code in the previous
slide is executed in an interpreter called JVM
The compiler first completely
translates the source program into target code
and saves it as an output target code file
However, unlike a compiler, an
interpreter executes commands one by one
That is, it does not create an output file
that has completed the translation like a compiler
Since JVM is relatively simple, it can be implemented without difficulty
Here we implemented JVM in Python
This “main” part should
actually be placed later in a Python program,
but let’s look at it first for easier understanding
To define the JVM's stack and variables as lists,
their sizes were set to 100 each
Stack pointer sp has an initial value of -1 and
maintains the index of the current stack top
And I initialized all the elements
of the stack and variable list to 0
Page 13 The bytecode program is stored as a list of two-digit
hexadecimal numbers,
as explained above
These hexadecimal numbers are read in order, changing the state of
the JVM and executing the program while interpreting it
The function responsible for execution is jvm_execute
After execution is complete, print the value of v[2] as the result
Page 14 The jvm_push
function is a function that pushes a
given value onto the stack
Increments the value of the current stack pointer (sp) and
assigns a value to that index in the
stack list The jvm_pop function returns the value of
stack[sp], which is the top of the current stack,
and decreases the value of sp, thereby decreasing the top index of the stack
Page 15 The jvm_execute function receives a list
of bytecode programs as a parameter, interprets
the commands one byte at a
time, and executes them
The global variable sp refers to the JVM's stack
pointer, and v is a variable array inside the JVM
PC is an abbreviation for "program counter",
and is an index used to read the bytecode program's instructions
one by one, and increases as the program is read
In the body of
the while
loop, each entry in the bytecode list is interpreted and the corresponding task is performed
For example, 0x3c is the “istore_0” instruction, which moves
the value at the top of the stack to v[0]
The remaining commands were also explained in the previous slides
Please take a look by following the bytecode program
Page 16
This table shows the differences between Compiler and Interpreter
First, in terms of translation
time, the compiler must finish compiling before
the target code is executed
However, the interpreter
translates line-by-line during execution
In terms of execution speed, the compiler is faster than the interpreter
Since a compiler executes a program after translation is complete, it
is significantly faster than an interpreter,
which executes the program line by line
When looking for errors, the
compiler can find all errors that can be found at compile time,
whereas the interpreter can only find errors in the
line currently being executed
In the case of the Compiler, an executable
file is created, but since the Interpreter is executed
line by line, an executable file is not created
Representative languages that use
compilers include C, C++, and Java (from source to bytecode)
Representative interpreting languages include Java (bytecode
execution), Python, JavaScript, and Ruby
Page 17 If we look again
at the execution process of a Java program, at compile time,
the compiler translates the Java source
code into a bytecode program
This bytecode program is executed line by line
by interpreting it within the Java Virtual Machine
(JVM), which is implemented in software
Because the interpreting process is relatively slow, various
devices have been studied to compensate for the speed
JVM has a device called JIT, or Just-In-Time
Compiler, to speed up interpretation
JIT compiles the byte code portions that are likely to
appear frequently into the machine language of the actual computer on
which the JVM is running
Later, when the byte
code part actually appears again,
it is possible to quickly execute it by using a pre-compiled machine language version
Page 18
Now, let's summarize the features of the Java language
First, Java is an object-oriented language with
classes as its basic unit
Additionally, the same source code can be executed
regardless of the type of computer hardware or OS using the
mechanism of bytecode and JVM
This characteristic is called “platform independence.”
The Java
language automatically collects
and reuses memory that is no longer being used during program execution
This feature is called “automatic garbage collection.”
This feature makes Java
easy to learn, as it doesn't have complex pointers or dynamic memory management like in C++
Because static typing is
used, strict data type rules must be followed,
which helps prevent programmer mistakes
Java also
has the ability to program jobs that are
smaller than processes, called threads, to run concurrently
Java provides excellent networking capabilities
and, with JIT, overcomes the limitations of the interpreter, enabling fast execution
As long as JVM is implemented,
it can be easily run on new platforms, and many useful standard libraries are provided
Page 19 To get a quick overview of the features of Java,
let's look at the
differences between the Java and Python languages
First, if we look at the program structure,
Python allows writing programs without using classes
Of course, the Python language also has
OOP concepts and can define classes,
but it is not necessary to use classes
However, in Java programs, everything must
belong to a class
In the case of this example program,
a single class called PythonVSJava makes up the entire program
Page 20 In terms of the type system,
the type of
a variable is not fixed in Python
In this example, variable x becomes an “integer” type the moment the
value 5 is assigned,
and when “Hello” is assigned to x again, x
changes to a String type
However, such free type change is not possible in Java
All variables have their types fixed before they are used,
and the types of variables cannot be changed during program execution
Also, in Python, there is no need
to declare the type of a variable before using it
However, in Java, a variable must be used after
it has been declared
Page 21 In Python,
functions are defined using the “def” statement
In Java, functions are implemented as methods belonging to a class
Page 22 Python
also has a class structure
A class contains variables and functions
In this example,
variables called name
and age are included in the class, and
__init__ and say_hello are functions
In particular, __init__ is a constructor that
is automatically executed
when a class object is created
In Java, the entire program consists of one or more classes
In this example, the
class Person has two data, name and age,
and has a constructor method Person and
a sayHello() method
Page 23 Python has a list structure
that is similar to the concept of a traditional array
The list structure is much more flexible than an array
and has many features
Java has a mechanism to create an array for each type
Also, if we use a collection framework
like ArrayList, we can use many more features
For code blocks on page 24,
Python expresses the same block with spaces
without using any separate delimiters
In the case of Java, the begin and
end are clearly indicated with braces
Page 25 In Python, the for loop performs
repeated operations on the elements in
a list
In this example, we perform repeated operations on the fruits in the list
called fruits and on the integers from 0 to 4
Similarly, in Java, the for loop allows us to perform repeated
operations on each element in an array
Additionally, we can perform operations while incrementing
the integer i from 0 to 4
Page 26 Both Python and Java use interpretation,
which inherently slows
down program execution
However, in the case of Java, mechanisms such
as JIT can be used to make execution faster
Python has a relatively simple syntax and is easy to learn
In comparison, Java has a very strict grammar,
which prevents programmers from writing
programs that contain errors without realizing it
Python includes library functions that are widely used in
science and engineering,
while Java has a rich standard library provided by default
and many third-party libraries for enterprise applications
Therefore, Python is widely used for
prototyping, data analysis, machine learning, etc
in research fields where execution speed is not important, and
Java is widely used for corporate solutions such as server implementation,
cloud implementation, Android application implementation, etc