Page 1
In this lecture, we will set up
the software environment
required to develop Java programs
It is easy to install and use,
so please follow along
Java Development Kit (JDK)
includes not only the JVM but also various tools
for Java program developers
For example, javac, i.e., the Java compiler,
java, i.e., the byte code interpreter, etc
A subset of the JDK intended only for program users,
not developers, is called the Java
Runtime Environment (JRE)
In other words, since users are not people who develop programs,
JRE can be seen as a JDK that excludes tools
used only for development
Sometimes, when you try to install and run a program developed in Java,
you will be prompted to download JRE if you do not have it
This is because JRE is essential for running programs
developed in Java
JDK and JRE
can be downloaded from
Oracle's Java Technology Site,
the owner of Java. Page 3
To download the JDK,
go to the Oracle Technology site
and click on the latest version of JavaSE. Page 4
Download and install the appropriate JDK
depending on whether your OS
is Windows, macOS
M Chips, or macOS Intel chips. Page 5
To check if the JDK is installed properly,
open a console window and run the command
java -version in it
If the Java version is displayed,
the JDK is installed correctly. Page 6
Documentation for APIs included in JDK
is provided
online by Oracle Visit docs.oracle.com/en/java/javase and click on
the JDK version you
installed. Page 7
Select API Documentation from the left menu area
On the Page 8 API Documentation
page, type the name of the desired class
in the search box to search
For example, you can search for a class called ‘System’
Page 9 The documentation for the ‘System’ class is displayed
Above the class name, the name of the package
to which the class belongs is displayed
For example, the System class is in the java.lang package
Fields contain descriptions of instance
variables or constants belonging to the class
Page 10
Below that, the methods belonging to the class are listed
so you can see how to use them
You can see the return type of the method, parameters,
and what it does
If you click on each method name,
you can see a more detailed explanation
Page 11 Before using the IDE that will be installed later, i.e
the Integrated Development Environment, let's
take a look at the process of compiling and running a Java
source program in the Console window
Write the source code of the Java program
using a suitable text editor
In this example, we created a class source
file called FirstProgram.java
The class name and the source
file name must match
Page 12 Type
the “Javac FirstProgram.java” command
in the console
to compile the source code into byte code
If compilation is successful, you can see that a bytecode program called
FirstProgram.class has been generated
To see a list of files in the current folder,
you can use the “dir” command on Windows
or the “ls” command on macOS
Now to run the Byte code program,
run the JVM interpreter “java FirstProgram” command
You need to type the command
excluding the
extension .class from the Byte code program
file name, FirstProgram.class
As the JVM runs, you will see the output
“Hello World!” printed to the console
Page 13
Now let's install the IDE, i.e
IntelliJ IDEA, the Integrated Development Environment
Download and install the “community
edition” of IntelliJ IDEA
from the JetBrains website
The community version is a free version
that has enough features for this course
Page 14 After installing IntelliJ IDEA,
run it and click the New Project button
Page 15 Enter a name for the project
and select the folder where you want to save
the project files
If you use Git, you can check “Create Git
repository” to automatically upload the completed source codes to GitHub
Let's not select this option here
If you have multiple JDK versions installed,
you can select the JDK you want
Usually, you can just select the latest version of the JDK that you have installed
The “Add sample code” option
is a feature that allows IntelliJ IDEA to automatically generate sample code,
but we will not select this option here
Once all inputs are completed,
click the “Create” button at the bottom
left to create a project. Page 16
You will now be taken to the project screen you just created
The src folder is empty
because we haven't created any source code yet
Page 17 Place the mouse pointer over the src folder
and press the right mouse button
to bring up a popup menu
Select New from the menu,
then select Java Class from the sub menu that appears
Page 18 When the New Java Class window appears,
type the class name you want to create
at the top and press Enter
Here, we entered the class name “TestClass”
Page 19
Now the “TestClass.java” source file is generated
I want to emphasize again that the class name
and the source file name must be the same
Now just type the program source into the source input
window. Page 20
Now, to compile the source file into bytecode,
select Build Project from the Build menu
The shortcut is Ctrl + F9 on Windows, or Command + fn
+ F9 on macOS
Page 21
You can now see an “out” folder
created in the file navigator on the left
“TestClass” is created under the out
> production > TestProject folder,
which represents the TestClass.class
file, which is a bytecode file
To verify that the bytecode file was actually generated,
check that the TestClass.class file was created
under the out folder
in explorer (Windows) or finder (macOS)
Page 22 To run the bytecode program
by running the JVM interpreter,
select Ctrl + r or click the Run button
(the play triangle)
You should see the program's output
printed in the terminal window
at the bottom of IntelliJ. Page 23
After you are done working, you can close the project
by selecting the “File > Close Project” menu
After closing the project, you can see
a list of all the projects you have
created and enter the project
by selecting each project with the mouse. Page 24
This time, we will learn how to import
already written source files into IntelliJ
Source files must be
in the format of having java source files
under the src folder
under the folder with the project name
Page 25 Select File > Open from the Main menu
and select the prepared project folder
Page 26 When the project is read and created by IntelliJ,
the source files will be placed under the src folder