In this lecture, we will cover the basic programming part
before the object-oriented part in the Java language
Page 2 First, let's look at
the general structure of a Java program
A Java program must define a class somehow,
because everything in it must be part of a class
In this example, a class called HelloWorld1 is defined
public is a keyword called an access modifier,
which means that this class can be used by any other class
class is a keyword that defines a class type
The class name follows, which in this example is HelloWorld1
As mentioned before, the class name
must match the name in the java source file
The class body begins with a left brace
Page 3 Inside the class body,
there are various fields that represent data
belonging to the class and methods that represent operations
The class in this example has no data, i.e. no fields
It has only one method, main
The main method is the first method executed when the program starts
Therefore, if it is an executable program (class),
it must have a Main method
The first thing that appears
in the header of the main method on page 4
is the access modifier, public
This public can be understood
as allowing the OS to call main to run the program
The static that follows indicates that the main method
is a static method within this class
In simple terms, this means that all objects created using this class
as a template share just one main method
It may be difficult to fully understand the meaning of static yet,
but we will learn more about it later
void means that the main method has no return value
Methods, that is, functions,
can often return a value or not
If there is a function f such that f(a, b)
= a + b, the return value could be a + b
However, some functions (methods) may only execute a series of tasks sequentially
without returning a value
main is the name of the method
The String[] args inside the parentheses after that
are the type and name of the parameter
In the previous example, the function
f(a, b), or method, takes two parameters
a and b and performs some calculation
For the Main method,
these parameters are called Command line arguments,
which are parameters attached to the command that runs the program
For example, if you run a program called “javac -version”,
javac is the name of the program
and -version is passed to the program as command line arguments
However, we are not using these command line arguments yet
The bracket symbol in String[]
indicates that args is an array type of String
For example, if we consider running the program “foo 3
Seoul 7”, args[0] = “3”,
args[1] = “Seoul”, args[2] = “7”
Page 5 Comments in Java have the same format as in C or C++
First, there are multi-line comments that start with a slash star
/* and end with a star slash */
You can also start with a slash double star,
in which case you can use JavaDoc,
one of Java's utilities, to automatically create API documentation
However, we will not discuss this further in this course
and you are encouraged to consult other references if necessary
A single-line comment starts with a double slash
// and everything on the same line is considered a comment until the end
Page 6
The following is about a statement block,
which starts with a left brace
This block serves to group
multiple statements that make up the body of an If,
for, or while statement, while creating a new scope for local variables
Of course, the beginning and end of the entire method can be considered as one block,
and the beginning and end of the entire class can also be considered as one block
We will discuss the scope of variables in more detail later
Page 7
The following is an identifier
An identifier is simply a name that a programmer must create,
such as a variable, constant, method, parameter, or class
Identifiers in Java follow the case sensitive rule
That is, if uppercase and lowercase letters of the alphabet are used, they are recognized as different identifiers
Also, keywords used in Java grammar cannot be used as identifiers
For example, class, public, void, etc
There are only two rules that must be followed
when naming an identifier:
it cannot start with a numeric character and no special characters
other than the dollar sign ($) and the underscore (_) can be used
However, there is a general convention for naming identifiers
in the Java language
It is recommended that variables and methods use camelCase, that is,
they start with a lowercase letter and capitalize the first letter
when the word changes, and class names use PascalCase, that is,
they start with an uppercase letter
and capitalize the first letter when the word changes
Page 8 There are two types of data types in Java
The first is the primitive type
and the second is the reference type
Primitive types are types
that basically have only one value,
such as integers and real numbers
Therefore, primitive types are not treated as classes
On the other hand, reference types refer to all classes
such as String, and types such as Array, enumeration, etc
Strictly speaking, a reference is a concept similar to an address in memory,
and can be seen as having the address of the memory where complex data
such as a class are gathered as its value
We will learn more about reference types later
There are four types of primitive types:
integer, real number, character, and boolean
There are four types of integers:
byte type of 8 bits (i.e
1 byte), short type of 16 bits (2 bytes), int type of 32 bits
(4 bytes), and long type of 64 bits (8 bytes)
There are 32-bit float and 64-bit double types
The character type is char, which is 16 bits
In Boolean type, there is a boolean type
that can have only one value, either true or false
Let's look at an example program for Page
9 Data type
First, I declared myNumber, which is an int type, and initialized its value to 10
In the case of yourNumber,
declaration and initialization are sometimes done at the same time
Literal refers to numbers, characters, strings, etc. that are directly given here
When assigning a literal to float type f1,
you must add f at the end of the number to distinguish it from double
Instead, when assigning a literal to a double type,
you can just use a number
Page 10 Let's look at a case
where we assign the value of a variable of a different
type to a variable of a different type
myInt is of int type
The value of myInt was assigned to myDouble, which is a double type
The reason why you can just assign without any other device at this time
is because the data range of double type is much wider than that of int
This method is called implicit conversion
The value 10 of myInt becomes 10.0 when assigned to double
On the other hand, when assigning myDouble to myInt,
you must explicitly convert by attaching the casting operator (Int)
When casting from double to int, the decimal point is discarded
and only the integer part remains
So the double value 9.78 is converted to the int value 9
Page 11 Named constants
are used to represent specific values as identifiers,
making their meaning clear
and allowing programs to use names instead of numbers
In this example, the value INCHES_PER_FOOT is defined as 12,
and since 1 foot equals 12 inches,
this value can be set as a constant
RATE is fixed at 0.14, and you can expect it to represent some specific rate,
such as an interest rate
In this way, once a named constant's value
is defined, its value cannot be changed within the program
Any attempt to change
this will result in a Compile error
Keywords such as public static final are attached,
and here final means constant
and indicates that the value cannot be changed
When naming identifiers that represent naming constants,
it is generally recommended to use only uppercase letters
and use underscores (_) between words
Page 12 The String type is a class type
included in the basic package provided by Java
It is a reference type used to handle text strings
The three Strings greeting, firstName, and lastName are initialized to “Hello World!”,
“John”, and “Doe”, respectively
Strings can be concatenated, or joined together,
using the plus operator
You can see that the value of the fullName String
concatenated in the example is printed on the screen
Page 13 For String concatenation,
you can concatenate not only Strings,
but also integer literals such as 42 into a single String,
like in this program
You can also concatenate variables of primitive types or class types,
such as int type k
We'll learn more about what makes this possible
as we study the class
Page 14 A string can be viewed from another perspective
as a collection of characters
However, this does not mean that a String is the same as an array of char types
In C or C++, these two are the same,
but in Java, String is not
However, each character that makes up a Java
String has an index
The 0-based index is useful in several String methods
that we will see later
Note that blank spaces are also considered
as characters
Page 15 The String class
has several methods
First, let's assume that the value of the str String is "Hello, World!"
length() returns the length of the String
If we look at the index of the previous page,
the index of the last character of the String + 1 is equal to the length
charAt(index) returns the character at position index in the string
In this example, charAt(0) returns the uppercase character H
substring(int) returns a subString from the given parameter index
to the very end of the String
In the case of “Hello, World!”,
substring(7) returns “World!” because it starts from Index
7, ‘W’, to the end
substring(0, 5) returns a subString from begin index 0 to end index 5
equals(String other) tests whether the String that
called equals is the same
as the contents of the parameter
other, and returns true or false
equalsIgnoreCase is like equals, but returns true
if they are the same regardless of case
Page 16 str.compareTo(String other) returns
a minus value if str is less than other, 0
if they are equal, and a plus value if they are greater,
based on the lexicographical ordering
str.indexOf(“World”) returns the starting index of the first substring named “World”
in the String str
str.lastIndexOf(“o”) returns the starting index of the last occurrence of “o” in str,
if the substring “o” occurs
str.contains(“Hello”) returns true if the substring “Hello” exists in str
str.replace() has several versions, and replaces characters,
substrings, etc
that appear in str with a second one
str.toUpperCase() returns str with all uppercase letters,
and str.toLowerCase() returns
str with all lowercase letters
Page 17 str.trim() removes all spaces from the beginning
and end of a string
This method is conveniently used when receiving text input in a UI such as the web
String.join(a, b, c) concatenates three Strings in the order b, a, c
String.valueOf(123) returns the integer 123 as the String “123”
Similarly, String.valueOf(true) returns the boolean value true
as a String “true”
str.startsWith(“Hello”) returns true if str starts with “Hello”
str.endsWith(“!”) returns true if str ends with “!”
str.isEmpty() returns true if str is an empty String
Page 18 Escape Sequence is used firstly
when you want to print characters
that are used for special purposes in the program
and secondly when you want to print invisible special characters
Double quote, single quote, and backslash are characters used for special purposes, and new line, carriage
return, and tab are invisible special characters
This example prints using the escape sequences backslash, new line,
double quote, Tab, and single quote
Page 19
Java Strings are immutable, meaning that the contents of a String cannot be changed
If you want to change the contents, use a StringBuffer object instead of a String
Of course, it is possible to change the contents of a String using assignment
This example shows assigning the contents of name to “Soprano”
and then changing it back to “Anthony Soprano”
Strictly speaking, in this case, the memory
originally allocated to name is maintained and its contents do not change
The principle that String is still immutable
is maintained because new memory space is allocated each time a new assignment is made
Page 20 The ASCII character set
is the one most widely used in existing computer systems
This character set contains all the characters found on the English keyboard,
plus some special characters
Since there are 128 characters in total,
the ASCII set can easily be represented in 8 bits
Based on this judgment,
programming languages prior to Java
often defined the size of the Character type as 8 bits (1 byte)
C and C++ are representative examples
Page 21
However, since it was impossible to represent all foreign language characters and various symbols
other than the English alphabet
with only 8 bits, Java represented each character with Unicode, which uses 16 bits instead of 8 bits
So, as you can see when you try it,
it is also possible to have variable names in Korean in Java programs
Of course, this course does not recommend using Korean variable names